<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe discourse, declaring and approuing the necessarie and inuiolable maintenance of the laudable customes of London namely, of that one, whereby a reasonable partition of the goods of husbands among their wiues and children is prouided: with an answer to such obiections and pretensed reasons, as are by persons vnaduised or euil persuaded, vsed against the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844454</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 406:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe discourse, declaring and approuing the necessarie and inuiolable maintenance of the laudable customes of London namely, of that one, whereby a reasonable partition of the goods of husbands among their wiues and children is prouided: with an answer to such obiections and pretensed reasons, as are by persons vnaduised or euil persuaded, vsed against the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henrie Midleton for Rafe Newberie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A briefe discourse of the laudable customes of London.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Estates (Law) --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="lat">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9268:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9268:1"/>
            <p rend="roman">A BREEFE Diſcourſe, declaring and approuing the neceſſarie and inuiolable maintenance of the laudable Cuſtomes of London: Namely, of that one, whereby a reaſonable partition of the goods of husbands among their wiues and children is prouided: With an anſwer to ſuch obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and pretenſed reaſons, as are by perſons vnaduiſed or euil perſuaded vſed againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Henrie Midleton for Rafe Newberie. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div rend="roman" type="legal_maxims">
            <pb facs="tcp:9268:2"/>
            <head rend="italic">Iuris ciuilis de conſuetudine Axio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata ſiue maximae.</head>
            <p>Conſuetudo vim habet rei Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae.</p>
            <p>Conſuetudo eſt optima legum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres.</p>
            <p>Conuentio &amp; conſuetudo vincunt legem.</p>
            <p>Conſuetudo firmata eſt vbi ſimili aliquando contradicto, Iudicio quid eſt obtentum ſeu Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</p>
            <p>Caepta vſucapio vel praeſcriptio per defunctum, continuatur per haeredem, cum in omne ius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functi ſuccedat haeres.</p>
            <p>Profunda requie humano generi proſpexit vſucapio. Barto.</p>
            <p>Vſucapio eſt quies periculi ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudiniſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> litium. Cicero.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9268:2"/>
            <head rend="roman">A BREEFE diſcourſe declaring and approuing the neceſſarie and inuiolable maintenaunce of the lawdable Cuſtomes of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E finde it neceſſarie in all common wealthes, for ſubiects to liue vnder the direction of Lawes, conſtitutions or cuſtoms publickly knowen and receiued, and not to depende only vpon the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and pleaſure of the gouernor, be the ſame neuer ſo iuſt or ſincere in life and conuerſation. For that the Law once enacted and eſtabliſhed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth his execution towards al men alike without fauour or affection: whereas if the word of a Prince were a lawe, the ſame being a mortall man muſt néedes bee poſſeſſed with thoſe paſſions, and inclinations of fauour or diſfauour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other men be: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times decline from the conſtant &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoueable leuell of indifferencie, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9268:3"/>reſpect the man beſides the matter, if not to regard the perſon more than the cauſe. Wherfore it was wel agréed by the wiſeſt Philoſophers and greateſt politicks, that a dumme lawes directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be preferred before the ſole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of any liuing Prince, both for the cauſe afore touched, and for other reaſons which I will here omit. But to deſcend to the particularities of my intention, and to treate of the validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and inuiolable obſeruation of ſome laudable (I might terme them ſacred) cuſtomes, being the principall ioyntes and verie ſinowes of all good corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and fellowſhips, and being alſo the mainteiners of a ſacred vnitie and natural amitie betwéene the huſband and his wife, the parentes &amp; their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which (as <hi rend="roman">Ariſtotle</hi> the wiſe Philoſopher termeth it) is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a citie. For what is a citie but a manifold and ioynt ſocietie conſiſting of many houſholdes, and liuing vnder the ſame Lawes, fréedomes and fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes? ſo I muſt néedes confeſſe them to be the procurers &amp; cauſes of ſundry
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9268:3"/>good effectes to the general eſtate of the citie wherein they be obſerued: as of the other ſide they may bréede ſundrie inconueniences in ſuch a citie where the ſame are violated and broken with allowance and impunitie. I will ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhortly ſhewe the nature of a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and the difference which it hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from a publicke Lawe. And next I will declare how neceſſarie the ſame are to manage the gouernment and to entertain the proſperitie and traffique of this citie: and namely that one good cuſtome which I entende to ſpeake of. Laſtly, I wil endeuour to aunſwere thoſe pretenſed reaſons, and couloura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obiections made againſt the preciſe maintenance and defence thereof.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I ſuppoſe that a Cuſtome which iuſtly deſerueth that name, is of no leſſe reuerent regarde and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie than a written lawe, paſſed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in Partliament: which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I doe graunt that there are certaine differences betwéene a lawe and a cuſtome: for the Cuſtome taketh his force by degrées of time, and conſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9268:4"/>of a certaine people, or the better part thereof, but a lawe ſpringeth vp in an inſtant, &amp; receiueth life from him that is of ſoueraigne authoritie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand. A Cuſtome enlargeth it ſelfe by plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible entertainement, and acceptable circumſtances of time &amp; occaſion, with generall liking and allowance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a Law is commanded and publiſhed by power and receiued by dutifull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, and that often againſt the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will of them that are bounde by it, for which cauſe <hi rend="roman">Chryſoſtome</hi> not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly compared the Cuſtom to a King, and the Lawe to a tyrant. Moreouer the Cuſtome doeth neither promiſe a rewarde for obſeruation, nor inflict a puniſhment for violation therof: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Lawe alwaies importeth either a conſideration of gaine, or a terror of puniſhment or damage, if the ſame be not a Lawe of enlargement or permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that diſanulleth the prohibitions of a former Lawe. Finally a Cuſtome is applyed to the commoditie of ſome one prouince, circuite or citie, and grounded vpon a ſpeciall reaſon of conueniencie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9268:4"/>or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, for thoſe perſons or place where it is obſerued: whereas the Lawe hath a generall reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">See 34. H. 8. B. cuſtome, 59. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not preſcribe or plead a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam angliam, for that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law &amp; no cuſtome, otherwiſe if the cuſtome had beene pleaded to be in ſuch a citie or countie as Gauelkind Gloc. Fee and ſuch like.</hi>
               </note> exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the whole Nation bound by the ſame, without priuate conſideration of the due importances, of any peculiar place or people. Therefore it is well ſaide and put in vre by the common Lawyer, <hi rend="italic">Quod conſuetudo ex rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili cauſa profecta priuat communem le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem. <hi rend="roman">That a Cuſtome grounded vppon reaſonable and honeſt conſideration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgeth or altereth the iudgement of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Law.</hi>
               </hi> So that in Cuſtomes the eſtate or condition of the people are to be reſpected, and ſuch Cuſtomes as are conſonant to reaſon, and moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to the eſtate and qualitie of ſuch people, are to be allowed. For example the Cuſtome of Boroughengliſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Burchengliſh.</hi>
               </note> yet in force in ſundrie places of Englande, whereby the younger ſonne is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite his fathers lande, hath taken ſtrength by this reaſon, that the father may (if he be not careles and ſecure to doe his children good) traine vp his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſonnes in ſome good trade or occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9268:5"/>by which they may bee able to get their owne liuing: whereas the youngeſt, by the impotency and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his yeares, may be perchaunce vnapt and vnable for ſuch inſtruction. And ſo the Cuſtome commendable that prouideth for the reliefe of the young and impotent. Alſo by an olde cuſtome of this lande, in ſundrie boroughes and townes, landes were deuiſable by wil, though the Lawes of Englande pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced ſuch deuiſes to be voide, and the reaſon was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">But ſee now the ſtatute of 32 H 8. ca 2 and 34. H. 8. c. 5. of Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> for that inhabitants of Boroughes or Cities, whoſe traffique and trade reſteth much vppon mutuall truſt &amp; credite, are oftentimes indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the time of their death. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was thought méete, that they might deuiſe their lande for the due ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction of their creditors, which to do, they were enabled by the Cuſtome. In <hi rend="roman">Kent</hi> and other places of this lande the Cuſtome of Gauelkind is maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which importeth an equall diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the enheritance to be made among all the brethren: a Cuſtome partlie grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a natural conſideration,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9268:5"/>for that al the ſonnes holde the like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of nature &amp; deſert with their parentes, in the which they haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall intereſt: and alſo ſuffered to take place in <hi rend="roman">Kent</hi> and other places of this lande in thoſe daies moſt inclinable to rebellion, to the intent to enféeble their forces, and to bring their great houſes and families to impuiſſance and decay, thereby to diſable and diſcourage them from ſuch vnlawefull and violent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes.</p>
            <p>And to come néerer to the matter, this famous and renowned citie of London hath many laudable and auncient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes: which though they derogate and differ much from the rules of the common Lawe, yet haue they béene not onely approoued by inuiolate expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of ſundrie ages, but alſo haue béene of olde ratified and confirmed by ſundry actes of Parliament, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Princes, and namely by the ſtatute of <hi rend="roman">Magna Charta,</hi> by theſe wordes following,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Magna char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. cap. 9.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi rend="italic">Quod ciuitas London habeat omnes libertates ſuas antiquas &amp; conſuetudines quas habere conſueuit,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9268:6"/>which is, <hi>That the citie of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue all their auncient liberties &amp; cuſtomes which they haue vſed to haue.</hi> The words folowing for other cities, &amp;c. be, <hi rend="italic">Quod habeant omnes libertates &amp; liberas conſuetudines ſuas,</hi> which ſignifieth, <hi rend="roman">that they ſhall ſtill retaine their liberties &amp; free cuſtomes,</hi> that is to ſay, their frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes &amp; immunities, as to be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of tolle, pontage, and ſuch like: Whereas the Citie of London hath prouiſion made by that eſtatute, for all vſages and cuſtomes whatſoeuer. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of London beareth oddes, and prerogatiue ouer other cities in England, being the <hi rend="roman">Metropolis</hi> or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Citie thereof, ſo are the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes of it no leſſe neceſſarie than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable members of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, in tranſporting our commodities into other lands, and enriching vs with the benefits and fruits of other countries. The citie of Rome, and Citizens of the ſame had that prerogatiue as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges ſo alſo in their executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for cauſes capital, that they ſhould not be crucified, being a death of great
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9268:6"/>torment and infamie, but only behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The benefit of which Cuſtome <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> claymed and obteyned in the time of <hi rend="roman">Nero:</hi> pretending that he was a citizen of Rome. The ſaide Citizens alſo by the dignitie and reputation of their citie were not for any tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or offence to be fettered, whipped, or ſcourged, which priuiledge likewiſe the ſaide <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> toke hould of, who being oppreſſed by the calumnious accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and outcries of the <hi rend="roman">Iewes,</hi> was by commandement of <hi rend="roman">Claudius Liſias</hi> the captaine to be examined by torture of whippes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Actes. 22.</hi>
               </note> what was the cauſe of that generall murmure and exclamation of the people againſt him: yet <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> by alleadging that he was a frée man of Rome, not onely deliuered himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iniurie and rage of the people, but alſo made the captaine much afraide of queſtion or puniſhment for the indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offered vnto him, ſo great was the maieſtie of that Citie, and ſo reuerent the reputation of all ſuch as were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted members thereof. <hi rend="roman">Athenaeus</hi> termed Rome in thoſe daies very fitly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9268:7"/>
               <hi rend="italic">Epitome totius orbis,</hi> an abridgement of the whole worlde, for the continuall concourſe and reſort of all nations thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We may deriue thence an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our purpoſe, that London bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing woorthie that title, <hi rend="italic">Epitome totius Angliae</hi> in reſpect of the neceſſarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire &amp; frequent aſſemblie of al eſtates therein, whether it be for Iuſtice by the Lawes of this land, which are here adminiſtred, or by trade of marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, which is here ſo great that it may be termed <hi rend="italic">totius occidentis emporiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> and chieflie becauſe of the fauorable and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſoiorne of our moſt roiall and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoueraigne, whoſe maieſties cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this is as it alwaies hath béene of her moſt noble progenitors: the ſame is no leſſe woorthy of ſundry preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which by Cuſtome and Charter it enioyeth aboue other Cities of this lande.</p>
            <p>We finde in our Lawe bookes that the ſcholers of Oxford claymed a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge by cuſtome to haue preferment of any houſe or lodging that was to be lette in the citie of Oxforde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">40. E. 3. fo. 17. Vide Brooke, Preſcr. 8.</hi>
               </note> &amp; the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9268:7"/>was allowed in the common place in Weſtminſter, where Iuſtice <hi rend="roman">Finchden</hi> a man of great reckoning at that time ſaide, that it is reaſon that they which are principal inſtruments of great good in the common wealth, ſhould haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall cuſtomes for the maintenance of their ſocieties: the like reaſon (ſaith he) ſerueth for the merchantes of the ſtaple in Weſtminſter, and alſo for the Iuſtices of Aſſiſes, or Iuſtices in eyre, to haue the like prerogatiue. Alſo it is not vnfitte to remember, that the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons of the lande haue diuers preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues aboue other ſubiectes, that is, they ſhall not bee ſworne when they paſſe vppon their Péeres, and if they bring an appeale, the defendant ſhall not wage battaile againſt them, and they are exempted out of all returnes in Iuries, and ſhall not be ſworne in Léetes, and all in reſpect of their digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and for the neceſſarie vſe of them in gouernement of the common wealth. So that perſons of néedefull employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the eſtate, haue alwaies béene ſauoured in all their honeſt Cuſtomes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9268:8"/>or preſcriptions, and eſpecially the Citizens of London, and the rather for the great preſumption and opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of their experience, who being trayned by harde education, in great vſe of ſeruice and affaires: and alſo by their trauaile and traffique beyonde the ſeas, by continuall negotiation with other Nations muſt néedes (by al reaſonable likelihoode) procure vnto themſelues great iudgement and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, to manage a politicke regiment in their citie, according vnto that verſe of the Poet <hi rend="roman">Homer</hi> in the beginning of his treatiſe of wiſe <hi rend="roman">Vliſſes</hi> his aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures remembring his trauaile into ſundrie Nations and Cities.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
               <l>Die mihi muſa virum captae poſt tempora Troiae,</l>
               <l>Qui mores hominum multorum vidit &amp; vrbes.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſenſe whereof may be wel ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Engliſh verſe without time thus:</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>All trauailers do gladly report great praiſe of Vliſſes:</l>
               <l>For that he knewe manie mens
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9268:8"/>maners, and ſawe manie cities.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which opinion of their pollicie and experience conceiued and approued by the noble Princes of this lande, in all ages doeth euidently appeare by the manner of their gouernment, whereat ſtrangers do no leſſe enuie than admire ſéeing ſo populous a citie, conteyning by true eſtimation more then <hi rend="roman">500</hi> thouſandes of all ſortes of inhabitants managed not by cruell viceroyes, as is <hi rend="roman">Naples</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Millaine,</hi> neither by proude <hi rend="roman">Podeſtà,</hi> as be moſt cities in <hi rend="roman">Italie,</hi> or inſolent Lieuetenantes or preſidentes, as are ſundry Cities in <hi rend="roman">France,</hi> (whoſe preſidents are noble men or captaines, hauing their perſons enuironed with a guarde of ſouldiers, and holding their cities poſſeſſed with a garriſon aſwell in the quieteſt calme of peace as in the hoateſt combuſtion of warre) but by a man of trade or a méere marchant, who notwithſtanding, during the time of his magiſtracie, carieth himſelfe with that honorable magnificence in his port, and enſignes of eſtate, that the Conſuls, Tribuns or pretors of <hi rend="roman">Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9268:9"/>(namely, when as the ſame was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a monarchie) much leſſe the <hi rend="roman">Podeſtà</hi> of any citie in <hi rend="roman">Italie</hi> neuer bare the like repreſentation of dignitie, and that not onely in peaceable ſeaſons but in time of greateſt warre: for ſuch cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite the Princes of this lande haue ſtil repoſed in their fidelitie and wiſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that we haue fewe examples in any chronicle of any noble man or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appointed to aſſiſt the L. Maior in his gouernment, much leſſe to bee ſole ruler or lieutenant for the time, were the ſtate neuer ſo troubleſome, and the affaires of neuer ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence and importance.</p>
            <p>And to adde a litle more in proofe of the ſingular good conceipt had of their ſeruice to the common wealth, and that the ſame hath in al ages from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt giuen them prerogatiue aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cities of this lande, wee reade in the vij yeare of <hi rend="roman">Henrie</hi> the vi,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">7. H. 6.32.</hi>
               </note> that in a <hi rend="italic">natiuo habendo</hi> brought by the Lorde to recouer his villen, it was adiudged a good returne made by the Shiriffe of London, that ſuch was the Cuſtome of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9268:9"/>London, that a villen hauing remained there the ſpace of one whole yeare and a day, could not be fetched or remoued out thence. For ſo great is the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of that place, that it giueth prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the villen or bondman againſt his lord while the ſaide bondman ſhall be reſiant there. Likewiſe it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a good cuſtome in the citie of London, that no attaint ſhould be maintained for a ſuppoſed falſe verdit giuen in that citie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">7. H. 6.32. &amp; the ſame caſe was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged in 2. E. 3.</hi>
               </note> In the which caſe the Shiriffe of London made returne vpon a writ of attaint ſued againſt a Londoner, that ſuch was and had béen alwayes the cuſtome of the citie, that no attaint ſhould be allowed againſt any commoner or other citizen of the ſame, for which cauſe he might not <hi rend="italic">ſaluis libertatibus</hi> without impeachme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their liberties, ſerue or execute the writ. Then was there a writ directed out of the Chauncerie to the Iuſtices of the Kings bench with expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to allowe to the Maior, Shirifes and Citizens all their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, immunities &amp; cuſtomes, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9268:10"/>out of that writ was a <hi rend="italic">Venire fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> directed to the Maior &amp; Shiriffes, whereby was day giuen them to come and make declaration of their cuſtom, at which day the parties plaintife and defendant being preſent, the Maior &amp; Shiriffes had full allowance of their cuſtoms, the Shiriffes were holden ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for their returne, and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties writ was abated, and himſelfe puniſhed by impriſonment for his vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. I haue here at large remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred this caſe, to the ende it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare both what credit and opinion of conſcience and trueth, the lawe aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the citizens of London, and alſo how carefull and vigilant the Maior &amp; Shiriffes haue alwayes béene to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue &amp; vphold their cuſtoms, although ſithence that onely cuſtome was for eſpeciall cauſes abrogated by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi rend="roman">11.</hi> H. <hi rend="roman">7.</hi> and an attaint giuen in London.<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">11. H. 7. ca. 21.</hi>
               </note> Moreouer, we finde it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in M. <hi rend="roman">2.</hi> E. <hi rend="roman">3.</hi> that whereas a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of London brought an appeale of robberie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">M. 2. E 3. cor. pl. 157.</hi>
               </note> and the defendant would haue tryed his innocencie by battaile,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9268:10"/>as he may in ſemblable caſe againſt another man, <hi rend="roman">Wilby</hi> then Iuſtice an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, that he was not to haue allowance of battaile in an appeale commenced by a citizen of London, for that by cuſtom of their citie they were exempted from it. The like appeale was ſued P. <hi rend="roman">20.</hi> E. <hi rend="roman">3.</hi> wherein the defendant made offer of the ſame tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">P. 20. E. 3. cor. pl. 125.</hi>
               </note> And although hee that ſued the appeale woulde haue ioyned battaile without regarde of this fraunchiſe, the Lorde Maior with the reſt of the corporation ſued a writ out of the Chauncerie reciting their cuſtome or franchiſe, and prayed allowance of it in diſturbance of the battaile <hi rend="roman">20.</hi> E. <hi rend="roman">3. Coron. 125.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a frée man or frée woman of London be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to Ludgate, they are to be excuſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ignominie of Irons, if they can finde ſuerties to be true priſoners, &amp; if the ſumme be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue an hundred pounds. Vpon the like reaſon is that cuſtome eſtabliſhed for the liberall and milde impriſonment of the citizens in Ludgate, whereby they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9268:11"/>haue indulgence &amp; fauour to go abroad into any place by <hi rend="roman">baſton</hi> as we terme it, vnder the garde and ſuperintenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of their kéeper, with whome they muſt returne againe to the Priſon at night, a cuſtome verily, though qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled with by ſome, and ſuppoſed to be the hinderance and delay of Iuſtice, &amp; oftentimes a meane to defraud men of their true debtes and executions, yet the ground thereof being well exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it wanteth not a ſound mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the courſe of reaſon (as I thinke.) For the preſcription or cuſtom is but a mitigation of the extremitie of their impriſonment, ſeruing rather for the expedition of their diſcharge &amp; ſpéedie ſatiſfaction of their creditours, than for any other purpoſe: ſo that this ſcope and licence in proper conſtruction and ſenſe of lawe, cannot be termed an enlargement or libertie. For to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the materiall priſon in the night, and to go foorth out of the ſame in the day, vnder the reſtraint &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll of a continuall kéeper, is alwaies an impriſonment, though exerciſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9268:11"/>with greater mildneſſe &amp; lenitie. And diuerſe cauſes there are to warrant the ſame in London rather than in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: the one is for that the citie of London ſtandeth chiefely vpon the traffique and intercourſe of merchants and the vſe of buying &amp; ſelling of their ſundrie commodities, which is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes perfourmed by themſelues but by their factours and ſeruants, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes one factor or agent ſerueth the turne of manie merchants, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is preſſed to ſundrie and ſeuerall accountes. Wherefore to the ende the priſoners may enforme themſelues v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their mutuall reckonings, both what they owe and what is due vnto them, and alſo that vpon conference &amp; account with their agents returning from other countreyes they may be made acquainted with the increaſe of their aduentures or commodities, it is neceſſarie they ſhould haue places of méeting which will not be ſo conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in a cloſe priſon, the ſame being no place of aſſemblie or frée acceſſe (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it being no common dutie in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9268:12"/>Gaoler to permit any perſon to come among his priſoners for any ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) and if the Gaoler were bound to endure or ſuffer ſuch common &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie repaire vnto his priſoners, yet wil it be no fit place for marchants to treat &amp; negotiate their cauſes which cannot be well determined without their bookes of accounts, and witneſſes of their contracts, and oft muſt the ſame be decyded before the maſters of their trades or companies. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this cuſtome made in furtherance of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all accounts doth verie much enable the priſoner to procure his libertie and pay his det. Alſo if the priſoner be poore and of himſelf vnable to pay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Vide 4. E 6. plo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> com. 36.</hi>
               </note> this toleration of their going abroad with the kéeper is a good meane for him to procure the almes and reléefe of other charitable people, thereby the ſooner to purchaſe his libertie. Whereby it appeareth what reckoning the lawe maketh of them, in conſideration of their great hazard by ſea (through dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhipwracke or piracie) and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture in ſtrange countreys (by falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9268:12"/>and negligence of factours) or by warres betwéene Princes, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences and miſchiefes whereof, are not ſo offenſiue or preiudiciall to anie, as to merchants, whoſe condition as it may by a fortunate voiage be much enriched, and aduaunced: ſo may it by any of the miſchaunces aforeſaid, be ſo empaired &amp; ouerthrowen, that it may turne himſelfe, his wife, and familie to vtter calamitie and diſtreſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the hope &amp; comfort of the wife (hauing commonly no aſſurance of ioynture in the citie, nor expectation of dower as other women haue) and alſo of the children (being for the moſt part borne to no great patrimonie, other than that which their fathers ſhall by their vertuous induſtrie acquire) doth onely depend vpon the fortune of their huſbands or fathers trauaile, it hath laudably and conſcionably béene obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for a cuſtome, and is yet by the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and better ſort religiouſly regarded that when any citizen of London dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, his wife ſhall haue the third parte of his goods, and the children another
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9268:13"/>third part, equally to be diuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his goods, and himſelfe another third part to diſpoſe by his laſt will &amp; teſtament at his pleaſure. A partition ſo reaſonable and grounded vppon ſo good conſideration, (the qualitie and eſtate of the Londoners conſidered,) that if it were not approued by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, but to be propoſed in the wiſeſt and higheſt court of Parliament, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were fit to haue the force of a law, I thinke no man (vnleſſe he were a <hi rend="roman">Timon</hi> by nature, or a <hi rend="roman">Diogenes</hi> by diſpoſition) no man I ſay poſſeſſed with common humanitie would gaineſay or impugne it. Doth not the common law now in force giue the huſband pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently by the intermariage al the goods and chattels of his wife, though the ſame be of the value of <hi rend="roman">10000.</hi> pounds, ſo that when ſhée is once his wife, the law diſableth her to giue or diſpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that was hers before? And ſhall not the huſband be bound by ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blable obligation of reaſon to leaue his wife the third part of his goods, and if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9268:13"/>the lawe be in that reſpect defectiue (as what law in the world, except the law of God, is without his imperfections?) ſhall not the cuſtome ſupply it in ſuch ſort that no barbarous and vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or cautelous, and vnkind practiſes by déede of gift, or otherwiſe, ſhall diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point or defraud the ſame? eſpecially here in London, where the good eſtate of men, for the moſt part conſiſteth in mouables, by reaſon of their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all trades and exchanges, ſo that their wiues cannot aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of their dowrie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called thirds, as they might if their huſbands were ſeaſed of lands in fée ſimple. Alſo the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſocitie betwéene huſband &amp; wife, is of that pretious eſtimate and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reputation before God and man, that there may not poſſibly a more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and ſtraite coniunction be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined among the children of men. <hi rend="roman">Charondas</hi> the Philoſopher calleth them <hi rend="roman">Homoſipios,</hi> which ſignifieth, fedde with the ſelfe ſame foode. And <hi rend="roman">Epimenides</hi> another Philoſopher cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them <hi rend="roman">Homocapuos,</hi> which is as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9268:14"/>much to ſay, as vſing the ſelfe ſame ſmoke, and the ſelfe ſame manger, &amp; as it were drawing the ſelfe ſame breath. Finally, the ſcripture giueth expreſſe charge to eche man to tender his wife with extraordinarie good offices by ſaying, <hi rend="roman">Thou ſhalt leaue thy father &amp; mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Matth. cap. 19 Mark. cap. 10. 1. Cor. cap. 7. Epheſ. cap. 5.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi rend="roman">and cleaue to thy wife.</hi> If the force of cuſtome did not enforce the matter, theſe onely conſiderations were ſufficient to proue, that there ſhould be nothing priuate, nothing pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, nothing proper, but euery thing in common, euery thing equally inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted betwéene the huſbande and the wife. The like though not equall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is commaunded by the Apoſtle to the <hi rend="roman">Colloſſ. 3.</hi> by the fathers towards their children. <hi rend="roman">You fathers be tender and louing vnto your children, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs ſée what account our common law hath made of the like cuſtomes, ſounded vppon the loue and affection betwéene man and wife. It was vſed of auncient time in Gauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind land, &amp; hath receiued the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9268:14"/>and iudgement of a good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cuſtome, that if the huſband be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted and executed for a felonie by him committed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">M. 8. H.3 preſc. 60.</hi>
               </note> yet ſhall his wife for the ſolace of her loſſe and deſolation haue her dowrie of his land,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">8. E. 2. Itin. can. preſcript. 50.</hi>
               </note> and alſo the heire ſhall inherite the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that olde ſaying: <hi rend="roman">The father to the bough, &amp; the ſonne to the plough,</hi> although the common lawe by rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous imputation to make men more fearefull to offende in crymes of ſuch quality,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">P. 35. H. 6.58.</hi>
               </note> extendeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t though not to the perſons of the wife &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet to their fortune ſo farre as it may turne to their vtter impoueriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>In the citie of Yorke there is a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, that the huſband may enfeoffe his wife of ſuch laude as he ſhall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, which though it be againſt the rule of the common lawe (which diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the huſband to conuey any lande to his wife) by feoffement or déede,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">12. H. 3. pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6.1.</hi>
               </note> yet by force of the cuſtome it was adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be lawfull and effectuall. Alſo the cuſtome of manie places in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9268:15"/>is, that the wife ſhall enioy the whole land of her huſband in name of her dowrie, as it appeareth by <hi rend="roman">M. Litt.</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Litt. ti. Dower</hi>
               </note> and the huſband cannot by any cautele or deuiſe defeate her ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And in ſome other countreys they haue the moitie or tene part, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by the common lawe the thirde part. In Northwales the cuſtome is ſo beneficiall for wiues, (that although they be ſure of their thirds of ſuch land as their huſbands ſhall chaunce to be ſeaſed of at any time during the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age) yet are they to haue the moitie or tone parte, not onely of his goods &amp; moueables, but alſo of his leaſes, be the termes thereof neuer ſo long. Not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yeres agoe the cuſtome of Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bean was alleaged and allowed by the court of the Kings bench,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">14. Eliz.</hi>
               </note> that the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or wife whether ſo euer of them did happen to ouerliue ſhould haue the inheritance or fée ſimple land of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſuruiuor, a cuſtome verily nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contrary to reaſon nor repugnant to religion, as no well diſpoſed or good huſband can denie, when he entreth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9268:15"/>into conſideration of theſe holie duties and good obſeruances that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and commaunded in holie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Read the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, ca. 5.</hi>
               </note> If then theſe cuſtomes beare ſway in ſundrie places, and are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely approued by iudicial ſentences, what citizen wilbe ſo ſenſeleſſe, what Londoner ſo looſe, what merchant or other fréeman ſo inconſiderate, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regardfull of his owne good eſtate, and ſo readie to defile his own neſt, as once to attempt or practiſe the violation or breach of ſo good a cuſtome? What is he who ſéeing the eſtate of London is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before other cities of the lande by the benefite and meanes of their moſt profitable cuſtomes, that will giue a daungerous example to abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the ſame and to call their vſages in queſtion? A cuſtome, if it haue béene once notoriouſly diſcontinued, or interrupted, loſeth the title and appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a cuſtome, and by inſtance gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the time when it was diſuſed lacketh a great part of his authoritie. Then vnnatural or at leaſt wiſe vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed is that citizen which to ſerue his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9268:16"/>priuate humor bringeth a generall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom either into queſtion by his fraud, or by his example into contempt. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious alſo is the preſident of one cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome called in queſtion to the ruine of the reſt: Namely, when as the citie by their counſell in her maieſties courtes of Weſtminſter, claiming the benefite of their cuſtomes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">See before in the caſe of robberie how carefull the citie was to auoide this danger and to preſerue their cuſtome, and alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe of the attaint before 7. H. 6. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred &amp; confronted, &amp; with a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terplea giuen by themſelues, that ſuch of their owne Aldermen &amp; commons haue by their déedes and deuiſes either diſaffirmed or diſanulled the ſame. A practiſe as of great condemnation in them that do it, ſo no doubt of great ouerſight &amp; incircumſpection in them that ſuffer it.</p>
            <p>But ſomewhat to ſatiſfie the idle cauils pretended to the contrarie ſaith ſome one, is not the generall lawe of England ſufficient to manage the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of London as wel as of all other ſubiectes, but that Londoners muſt haue priuate cuſtomes and vſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their owne? This obiection made by the enuiers or enimies of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9268:16"/>wealth of London (howſoeuer they make ſhewe to the contrarie) rather deſerueth a hiſſe than a replye, and is ſufficiently confuted in the former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>But it is further vrged by ſome hard huſbands, my wife is frowarde &amp; vndutifull, and hath not deſerued it. Shée is a foole and cannot rule it. Shée will marrie againe, and enrich ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the fruite of my trauaile. Wherefore I thinke it neceſſarie to abridge her of that liberalitie which the cuſtome doth extende. Alſo my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be euill enclined, diſobedient or vntractable, or ſome of them be. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may with reaſon depriue them of the benefit of this cuſtome. Firſt to anſwere the vndutifulnes, I wiſh thée whoſoeuer thou art to ſummon and conuent thy ſelfe to the tribunall ſeate of thy inwarde minde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Aug. in lib. confeſſ.</hi>
               </note> as <hi rend="roman">S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaieth, &amp; to make conſcience thy iudge, thy cogitations the witneſſes, thy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the accuſers, thy memory the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or record to giue in euidence: and let it be diſcuſſed in all due circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9268:17"/>whether thou didſt not likewiſe forget the offices of a good huſband and defraud her of her duties,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">1. Corinth. ca. 7,</hi>
               </note> (as <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> ſayeth) or prouoke her to impacience which the ſame Apoſtle forbiddeth in theſe wordes, <hi rend="roman">You husbandes be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to your wiues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Coloſſ. ca. 3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi rend="roman">and no way be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Peter. Epiſt. 1. ca. 1.</hi>
               </note> Which alſo <hi rend="roman">S. Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth in aduiſing huſbandes to dwell with their wiues ſincerely and according to knowledge in doing honor vnto them as to the weaker veſſell. Let it I ſay bee examined in the conſiſtorie of thy conſcience whether thou either by thy fault wittingly, or negligently by thy default, or by thy vnkindneſſe vnduly, haſt cauſed her being the weaker veſſell to be the more intollerable. If thou finde thy ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by thy conſcience, let remorſe be thy executioner, and amendment with kindneſſe towardes thy wife be thy penance: but if thou finde thy ſelfe guiltie of no want of affection, loue or good cariage of thy ſelfe towardes her, ſo that her vndutifulneſſe procéeded of her ſelfe: yet I pray thée remember
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9268:17"/>the benefits which God hath giuen thée by her meanes, whether they be giftes of fortune in bettering of thy eſtate, or eſchewing of ſinne, by her lawfull and comfortable companie, or the bleſſing of children a ſoueraigne good in this worlde, thy children being the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy life and being vpon earth, &amp; the repayrers of thy decaie. And let theſe fauours and graces enioied by her company couer and counteruaile her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imperfections whatſoeuer. Folow therein the example of the wiſe <hi rend="roman">Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> who being demanded how he could endure the continuall ſcoulding &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his wife <hi rend="roman">Zantippe,</hi> likewiſe aſked of the other why he ſuffered the rackling and vnpleaſant noyſe of hens and Turkeies in his houſe, becauſe ſaid the other they lay egges and bréed chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens for me, and ſo ſaid <hi rend="roman">Socrates, Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tippe</hi> beareth me children, which good turne alone couereth and diſpenſeth with infinite defectes. <hi rend="roman">Calicratides</hi> the Athenian being demaunded why he a man ſo nobly deſcended, but hauing matched with a baſe <hi rend="roman">Theſſalian</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9268:18"/>yet by his laſt will bequethed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her all his ſubſtance, leauing his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friendes and kinſfolkes vnregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: becauſe (ſaide he) ſhe is my wife, meaning that ſhee who was by his iudgement and choice made woorthie to be his wife, ſhould be vnwoorthie of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was his. Which may alſo ſatiſfie that ſeconde point of ſuppoſed folly in the wife, and want of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to marſhall ſo great a proportion of wealth, as the cuſtome will giue her. Wherefore wouldeſt thou marie with a foole, if thou thoughteſt her vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the rights of mariage? then ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy choice hath eſtopped thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of her folly, thy dutie towardes thy wife ſhall binde thée to fauour and conceale her weakeneſſe, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which the cuſtome pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to be conuenient. It can not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill beſtowed vpon her, whoſe right by cuſtome demaundeth it, and whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and imperfections haue néede of it, whereas if the huſband may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by this colour to defeate his wife, many inconueniences and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9268:18"/>might enſue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Leges ſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modant ad ea quae fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentius non quae raro ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidunt. Bartolus.</hi>
               </note>Firſt a generall Cuſtome, which is as alſo a generall Lawe neuer proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ſuch rare accidentes as ſeldome fall in experience, but for thinges that ordinarilie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly happen, ſhould be broken, to the generall ſcandale and offenſiue example of all through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habilitie of one, which were a thing vnreaſonable. Likwiſe then might huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes, (if that were admitted for a iuſt allegation) eaſilie deuiſe and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe that or ſome other imperfection to be in their wiues, and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue them of their right. No more then it is a iuſt counterplea or barre to a womans dower to alleadge that ſhée is a foole, no more is the imputation of ſuch ſimplicitie honeſt and ſufficient to exclude her from her portion. No it is wel ſaid and maintained for a <hi rend="roman">maxime</hi> in the common Lawe, <hi rend="roman">Better it is to ſuffer a miſchiefe than an inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Leſſe harmeful and hatefull it is for a man to ſwallowe twentie of theſe light offences, and to diſgeſt ſundrie of theſe pretenſed ſcruples, than by viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9268:19"/>of a cuſtome no leſſe common than commendable to leaue to poſteritie an odious memorie and obloquie of his name.</p>
            <p>The laſt obiection againſt wiues is no leſſe ridiculous than Tyrannicall, grounded vpon an vniuſt deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them from mariage. Mariage is an honorable ordinance of God, fit and neceſſarie for all perſons diſpoſed thereunto, to the auoyding of ſinne, and maintenance of a comfortable and ſociable chriſtian life. To reſtraine or prohibit the ſame either in maides or widowes, (as <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> ſayth) is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of diuels.<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Tim. ep. 1. ca. 4</hi>
               </note> And to indent or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with any that he or ſhe ſhall not marie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">43. E. 3.6.</hi>
               </note> is a condition limited againſt lawe, and by the ſame pronounced vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and vnreaſonable. Make it thine owne caſe, admitte thou diddeſt match with a welthie wife, whoſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture and riches hath increaſed thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, if God ſhould call for her, woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou in a kinde memoriall of the benefittes attained by her meanes, make thy ſelfe a votarie to liue vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9268:19"/>Doe thoſe which marie great heires being women, and after their wiues deathes enioy their whole inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance by the curteſie of England, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their wiues heires to expect du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their liues, take it for any matter of conſcience or ſcruple to marie again? Vnleſſe it be in ſome place where the force of the cuſtome and the benefit of the liuing ioyned together worke a contrarie reſolution in ſome huſbands: which Cuſtome annexed to Gauelkind landes in <hi rend="roman">Kent</hi> and other places is of this qualitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">16. E. 3. aid 129 19. E. 3. aid 144</hi>
               </note> that the huſband ſhal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the deſeaſe of his wife be tenant by the curteſie of her lande as long as he remaineth vnmaried, whether he haue iſſue by her or not: but vpon his next mariage ſhall vtterly forgoe all his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt therein. A cuſtome therefore the leſſe vnreſonable becauſe the reſtraint of mariage of the one ſide is counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed by the beneficiall fauour of the other ſide to haue the land by the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie without iſſue, and alſo for that he is to depriue the next heire of his wife, who perchance hath béen maried with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9268:20"/>him but fewe moneths or daies, of the profite and commoditie of the whole land during his life. But chiefly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a cuſtome grounded &amp; gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in continuance to ſuch religious obſeruation &amp; regard, that it ſéemeth an offence of conſcience to infringe it. But in our caſe ſithens there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cuſtom nor conſcience to warrant thy wil, why ſhouldeſt thou then ſéeme to quarell with the lawfull libertie of thy wife, if ſhee ſuruiue thée, ſhée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weake by kind and education, and thereby leſſe able to direct her occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and gouerne her eſtate without a companion and coadiutor? no on Gods name referre her to her owne choyce &amp; conſcience therein, and make it no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and colour to abridge her of her right, becauſe ſhée ſéemeth inclynable vnto that, which God hath ordained, &amp; all men and women do embrace. As to the feare and ſuſpition pretended, that another in matching with thy wife ſhould be enriched by thy trauaile, what ſhould moue thée to make that ſuperſtitious account of thy goods whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9268:20"/>thou art gone? Were they any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thine, than while thou hadſt life &amp; licence to employ them? Thou muſt néedes knowe &amp; acknowledge beſides thy daily experience, by the verie Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie and ſignification of the word, the true nature &amp; qualitie of the thing. Theſe worldly goods are called tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, becauſe they ſerue one but for a time, they are termed tranſitorie, for that their property is fléeting from one owner vnto an other, they are named moueable or currant, becauſe all their grace and credite is in running &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing into diuers handes, according to that rude and olde (but yet true) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ryme,</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
               <l>Omnia mundana per vices ſunt aliena,</l>
               <l>Nunc mea nunc huius, poſt mortem ſunt alterius.</l>
            </q>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>This worldly wealth each day doeth change</l>
               <l>Their owners as we ſee,</l>
               <l>Nowe mine nowe his and after death</l>
               <l>An others goods they be.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Then ſithence thy wealth hath way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon thée all thy life long, wouldeſt thou require the ſame to reſt at thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9268:21"/>after thy death? If that ſéeme impertinent and vnprofitable vnto thée then relinquiſh this care and ſuffer the goods of this world to haue their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall courſe and condition, which is to be ſtill in exchange, paſſage, &amp; poſting from hande to hande, ſeruing all men, <hi rend="italic">vt peregrinationis viaticum,</hi> That is, <hi rend="roman">A pilgrimes charge or defrayment in his iourney,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Hieronymus in Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> as <hi rend="roman">S. Hierome</hi> termeth it. And addreſſe thy minde to the deſire of ſuch goods as are neither temporall, tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, currant nor moueable, but perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, permanent, conſtant and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immutable but ineſtimable.</p>
            <p>But finally to ſatiſfie the laſt obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt thy children, I wiſh thée to looke backe vnto that I haue ſaide, that thou mayeſt not for a priuate iniurie or diſpleaſure, ſéeme as much as lyeth in thée to ſupplant and abrogate a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke cuſtome, to the no leſſe preiudize than offence of a great number that haue intereſt therein. In enriching thy ſonne, thou doſt diſcharge the duty of a naturall father towardes him, which if he prodigally or wickedly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9268:21"/>or abuſe, he carieth his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and prooueth a wilfull ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to himſelfe. The good father men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned of in the goſpel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Luke. cap. 15.</hi>
               </note> who at the ſuite of his vndutifull &amp; diſobedient ſonne, (that wold néedes abandon the ſeruice and attendance on his father to runne the courſe of an extrauagant libertine with lewd companie) gaue him a great portion of his wealth, is not any way blamed by our Sauiour for that indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but rather recommended to all poſteritie as a true paterne of a kinde father. <hi rend="roman">S. Paule</hi> commaundeth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be well affected to his children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Colloſſ. cap. 3</hi>
               </note> and no way to diſcourage them. What may bréede greater diſcouragement or diſcontentment in any childe than to ſée himſelf by the place of his birth and the good fortune of the citie intitled to the commoditie of a good cuſtome, and yet iniuriouſly by his owne father, (whoſe affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be alwaies occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied and earneſt in procuring the good of his children) diſappointed of his hope and defrauded of his right. And as well as ſome hauing iuſt cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9268:22"/>againe their ſonne and childe, may in this vnlawefull and diſorderly ſort practiſe their reuenge, ſo may ſome other inconſiderate and wilfull father vpon a conceipt taken againſt a good ſonne and of ſingular deſert, for that he concurreth not with him in ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor or diſpoſition, moſt wrongfully di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and vndoe him by ſuch a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Thus the miſchiefes obiected on the one ſide are light and of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereas the inconueniences ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant on the other ſide be manifolde and of dangerous conſequence.</p>
            <p>I will not vouchſafe to anſwere that vndiſcrete <hi rend="roman">Sarcaſmus</hi> or bitter ſcoffe that ſome vſe, <hi rend="roman">We may play our wealth at dice without offence to the cuſtome, wherefore ſhoulde wee not then diſpoſe the ſame from our wife and children</hi> by our déedes of gift? This amounteth to as much as if a maried man would ſay, I may commit fellonie or treaſon, and be attainted and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therefore, and then the law giueth my wife no dower, nor my heire no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, then why ſhould I not in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9268:22"/>reaſon vſe my diſcretion with the land without incumbrance by the one, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury to the other? Match theſe two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes togither with iudgement, and thou ſhalt perceaue they haue a ſenſible concurrencie in their addreſſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to this purpoſe. It is wel ſaid by the Poet,</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Nil iuuat exemplum quod litem lite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluit.</q>
            <p>The example of one wilfull or wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked act giueth no iuſt countenance or allowance to an other. Let ſo much ſaide to thy obiections take ſome place to alter thine humor, or at leaſt be a preparatiue for thine owne reaſon in the feare of God to purge thée of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this ſhort diſcourſe with one conſideration of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I wiſh thée to conſider, that this citie of London is and hath béene hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily preſerued in this flouriſhing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie by the wiſe and politicke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that all and alwaies the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers haue had to increaſe the generall good eſtate thereof, thinking it their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9268:23"/>dutie as they gotte and acquired their ſubſtance in this citie, ſo alſo to ſpend &amp; defraie it in the ſame: inſomuch that whatſoeuer falleth from the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth &amp; groweth vnto an other, and by alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of priuate fortunes (as chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; changes of times do require from one citizen to another) the generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate hath flouriſhed and neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted particular men of wealth &amp; habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſuſtaine the offices &amp; functions of the citie. Vpon which conſideration by moſt laudable &amp; auncient cuſtome, the L. Maior and Senate of London haue béene and are intitled to the tuition &amp; cuſtody of young <hi rend="roman">Orphanes</hi> and their goods, &amp; likewiſe are made acquainted by ordinarie good meanes of inuento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries taken &amp; produced, what ſubſtance and wealth ech man dieth poſſeſſed of, to the intent that although that man which by his good trauaile &amp; trade hath growen to be rich among them, be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted hence, yet his goods may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as among his wife &amp; children in vſe and propertie, ſo to the generall ſtrength of this city in account &amp; recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9268:23"/>For we often ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one rich mans wealth paſſeth to the increaſe of the good eſtate of an other citizen, either by mariage of the widowe, or of the <hi rend="roman">Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane:</hi> ſo that the citie though depriued of a member or inhabitant, yet is not deſtitute of ſuch as may diſcharge his employment and place. Whereas if this pernitious practiſe &amp; vncharitable liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might take roote by déedes of giftes &amp; cautelous conueyance to ſtrangers, not only the wife &amp; children may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſted, but alſo the ſtate of the citie much weakened, &amp; in danger of a great diſreputation and decay, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that that it hath béene and yet is. For if it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged lawefull in one, of what degrée ſoeuer he be, it is neither impoſſible nor vnlikely that the ſame will be vſed by many, and conſequently may be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by all: which if it befall, what will become of the happie condition of this Citie, it is not hard to coniecture. I meane not to extende my ſpeach to the preiudice of any true debtes that a man oweth without fraud or colluſion, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cuſtom very prouidently careth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9268:24"/>for the diſcharge thereof, but my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to diſwade men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, from inſolent violation of good cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and from odious and vnſéeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſes of deceipt &amp; euill meaning towardes their wiues and children: Which perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I would wiſh al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Lawe ſeriouſlie and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to vſe and enforce to their clients, being citizens of London, as in good conſcience and diſcretion they ought to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">An Apoſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe to the reader, and the motiue of this treatiſe.</hi>
               </note>Blame not my bold enterpriſe (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) nor reproue my ſimple cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure herein preſented vnto thée, which might I knowe both for the matter and manner of it haue béene by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and perchaunce by my ſelfe more largely and effectually deliuered: if the opportunitie of my leaſure might haue aunſwered the qualitie of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I had in hande. But fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leaſt I ſhould with too long a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in ſo plaine a propoſition bréede more lothſomeneſſe than liking, I would not, for want of leaſure I might
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9268:24"/>not, &amp; if I had had time at will I min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not, ſéeing for any vrgent occaſion (the error being yet freſh, the practiſe rare and not growen to an enormitie, I néeded not) but in a worde or two to make thée acquainted with the cauſe that moued me to addreſſe theſe fewe reaſons to thy gentle view. So it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that I being in company &amp; confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with ſome perſons (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wiſe and well affected, yet in this matter ſtrangely conceipted) it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that the lawefulneſſe and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of this cuſtome came in queſtion and debate among vs, &amp; was by ſome of them (being men for ſufficiencie, of great opinion, and for countenance and credite of good apparance and regarde in the citie) ſo preſſed with obiections, that the moſt part of thoſe which were preſent ſéemed to encline to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. Wherefore leaſt the authoritie of the men might the ſooner ſeduce the ſimple multitude vnto their error, &amp; for that I thought it a charitable pollicie to preuent the peril in the prime, before it grewe to a feſtering ſore or incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9268:25"/>euill, according to the Poet <hi rend="roman">Ouids</hi> aduiſe,</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">
               <l>Principijs obſta ſero medicina paratur,</l>
               <l>Cum mala per long as inualuere moras.</l>
            </q>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Withſtand at firſt the ſpringing euill</l>
               <l>With medicins fit therefore,</l>
               <l>Too late it is to take the cure</l>
               <l>Of old and feſtred ſore.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I thought good to apply this ſimple reſceipt of reaſon to the mindes of all ſuch as ſhall chaunce to be diſtempered by theſe diſuaſions: hoping that they wil yéelde me that friendly requitall of good conſtruction, which my offered goodwill may ſéeme to deſerue: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I kéepe my ſelfe vnnamed, and vnknowen: it may pleaſe them to haue this opinion of me, no more fauourable than reaſonable, that he which is well deuoted to the defence of good cuſtoms, is rather to be iuſtified in his good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, than condemned or held ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of anie ſiniſter conceipt.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi rend="italic">FINIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9268:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
